[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
hey this is jeremy jung for software
engineering radio
today i'm talking to scott hanselman
he's a
partner program manager at microsoft the
host of over 750 episodes of the hansel
minutes podcast
and he's got a youtube channel he's got
a lot of interesting videos
one of the series i really enjoy is one
called computer stuff they didn't teach
you
you're all over the place scott welcome
to software engineering radio
thank you for having me yeah i was an
adjunct professor for a while and i
realized that in all of my career
choices and all of my
uh volunteerism and outreach it's just
me trying to get back to teaching
so i just started a tick tock so i'm
like the old man on tick tock now but
it's turned out to be really great and
i've been
got to engage with a bunch of people
that i would never have found on any
other social platform
so whether you find me on my podcast my
blog which is almost 20 years old now
my youtube or my tic toc or my twitter
it's pretty much the same person
i'm a professional enthusiast but that's
all done in the spare time because my
primary job is to
own community for visual studio that
experience of
being a teacher in so many ways is one
of the big reasons why i wanted to have
you
on today because i think in
the videos and things you put out you do
a really good job
of explaining concepts and just making
them approachable so
i thought today we could talk a little
bit about
ned and what that ecosystem is because i
think there's a lot of people who
they know.net is a thing they know it
exists but they don't really
know what that means so yeah maybe you
could start with defining like what what
is
net sure microsoft is historically not
awesome at naming stuff
and i joke about the idea that 20 years
ago microsoft took over a top-level
domain
right thereby destroying my entire dot
org plan to take over the world
when they made the name.net they were
coming out of com
and c and c plus involved component
object models
and they had made a new runtime while
java was
doing its thing in a new language in a
new family of languages
and then they gave it a blanket name so
while
java was one language on one runtime
which allowed us to get very clear and
fairly understandable
acronyms like jre java runtime
environment and jdk
microsoft came out of the gate with
here's.net
and c-sharp and vb and cobalt.net and
this and that and this is a
multi-language runtime in fact they
called it a clr
a common language runtime so rather than
saying
here's c sharp it's a thing they said
here's dot net and it can run any one of
n
number of languages now the reality is
that if you
look over time java ended up being kind
of a more generic runtime and people run
all kinds of languages on the java
runtime dot net now has c-sharp which i
think is arguably first among equals
as its language although we also have vb
and an f-sharp as well as a number of
niche languages but the net
larger envelope name as a marketing
thing
remains confusing if they had just
simply said
hey there's a thing called c sharp it
probably would have cleared things up
so yeah sorry that was a bit of a long
answer and it didn't actually get to the
real answer
bear with me so i mean you had mentioned
how there was this run time that c sharp
runs on top of
is that the same as the the jvm like the
java virtual machine
right so as with any vm whether it be v8
or
the jvm when you could take c-sharp
and you compile it you compile it to an
intermediate language we call it il
java folks would call it a byte code and
it's basically
a processor non-specific assembler for
lack of another word if you looked at
the code
you would see things like load four byte
string
into you know pseudo register type of
stuff
and um you would not be able to identify
that this came from c sharp it would
just look like this kind of
middle place between apples and apple
juice it's kind of applesauce it's
pre-chewed but not all the way
and then what's interesting about
c-sharp is that when you compile it
into a dll a dynamic link library which
is like a shared object
where you compile it into an executable
the executable contains that il
but the executable doesn't know the
processor it's going to run on
that's super interesting because that
means then i could go over to an arm
processor or an intel x86 or an x64
or whatever an iphone theoretically and
then
there's that last moment and then that
jitter that just in time compiler
goes and takes it the last mile that
local runtime
in this case the clr the common language
runtime takes that
il chews it finally up into apple's
apple juice
and then does the processor specific
optimizations that it needs to do now
this is a
over simplification because the the
pipeline is quite long
and uh pretty exquisite in fact for
example if you're on
varying levels of processor on varying
versions of x64
or on an amd versus on a an intel
machine
there's all kinds of optimizations you
can do as well as switches that we can
do
as developers in config files to give
hints
about a particular machine is this a
server machine
is this a client machine is it memory
constrained does it have a
you know 64 processors can we prep this
stuff
both with a naive jit a naive
just-in-time compilation
or then over time learn literally
learning over the
runtime cycle of the process and go you
know i bet you we could
optimize this better then swap out
in while it's running a new
implementation so we can actually do a
multi-layered
jit so here's the i want to start my
application
fast and run this for loop you know this
for loop's been running for a couple of
thousand milliseconds and it's kind of
not awesome
i bet you we can do better then we do a
second pass swap out the function table
drop a new one in and now we're going
even faster so our jitter particular
64-bit jitter is really quite
extraordinary in that respect
that's pretty interesting because i
think a question that a lot of people
might have is what's what's the reason
for having this
intermediary language and not compiling
straight to machine code
and what it sounds like what you're
saying is that it can actually at
runtime figure out like how can i
run things more efficiently based on
what's being executed in the program
right
so when you are running a strongly typed
language
that has the benefits and the speed of a
patrolling type language
and you also choose to compile it to a
processor specific representation
we usually as developers and deployers
think about things in terms of
architectures like this is for an arm
processor
but is this a raspberry pi is it an
android device
do you really want to get down to the
stepping individual versions of like in
intel
for example i'm talking to you right now
on an intel i9
but it's a desktop class processor that
was the first one released
many many years ago it doesn't have the
same instruction set as a modern
i9 or a xeon or something like that so
we have to be able to know what
instruction sets are available and do
the right thing then if you add in
things like
simd or doing you know data
parallelization as the cpu level
if that's available we might treat a
vector of floats differently than we
would on another thing
so how much information up front do we
know about deployment
and is it worth doing all that work on
the developers machine
and this is the important part which may
not necessarily reflect
the reality of where it's going to get
deployed you know my desktop does not
represent
a machine in azure or heroku or aws so
getting up to the point where we know as
much as we can and then letting
the the runtime environment
adapt to the true representation of
what's happening on the
on on the final machine that doesn't
mean that we can't go and do
native compilation or what's called
engine
or native image generation if we know a
whole lot
but it provides a lot of value if we
wait until the end
yeah that's an interesting point too in
that
if we are compiling down to an
intermediate language
on our own development machines then we
don't have to worry about like having
all these different targets right of
saying i'm going to build for this
specific type of arm processor
you know all these different places that
our application could possibly go
because the runtime
is taking care of that for us right and
i think it's one of those things where
it's taking
care of it for us unless we choose to it
reminds me of the time
if you remember when we went from you
know mostly manual shift cars
to automatic shift cars but people who
bought fancy audi's and bmws were like
you know
when i'm going to the the shops to get
groceries i'm cool with
automatic but i really like the ability
to downshift
and then we started to see these hybrid
cars that had you know d and
r for drive and reverse and then a
little move left and move right to take
control and like
i'm going to tell the automatics you
know transmission on this car that i
really want to run at a higher rpms
dot net tries to do that it gives you
both the ability to just say you know
do what you're going to do i trust the
defaults but then a ton of switches
if you choose to really know about that
ending environment
we've been talking about the common
language runtime which i believe you
said is the equivalent
of the java virtual machine you also
mentioned
how there are languages that are built
to
target the intermediate language that
that runtime
uses like c sharp and vb and things like
that and you touched on this earlier
before but i feel like we haven't quite
defined what dot net really is like is
it that run time and so on
yeah okay my apologies yeah
okay so dot net is an aw as an
all-encompassing
marketing term i would say is the
ecosystem
just as java is a language and also an
so when someone says i know.net i would
assume that they are at the very least
familiar with c-sharp
they know how to compile code and deploy
code they might be able to
be a website maker or they might be an
iphone developer
that's where net starts getting
complicated because it is an ecosystem
someone could work let's say two people
could work for 10 years in the ecosystem
and one could be
entirely micro services and containers
on the back end in the cloud
and the other person could be android
and unity and games
and xbox and they are both net
developers except they never
touched each other's environment one is
entirely
a game and mobile app developer and the
other one is entirely a back-end
developer
that's where it's harder now i think the
same thing is true in the java world
although i would argue that you would
you'd be surprised how many places that
you can find
net whether it be in a python notebook
you can run.net and c-sharp and an ipymb
in a notebook in jupyter on you know on
the google cloud or you can run it
on a micro controller not a
microprocessor but literally
on a tiny 256k micro
controller all of that is is.net now.net
is also somewhat unique amongst
ecosystems in that it has a very large
what we call bcl the base class library
one of the examples might be that we
know with a python or with a javascript
you say
console.log hello world we've got the
same thing
and then it's like hey i need a really
highly optimized
vector of floats with a complicated math
processing well you have to go and
figure out which one of those
libraries you want to pull in right
there's lots of options in the python
world there's lots of options in the
java world
the javascript world but then you have
to go hunting for the right library you
have to start thinking
microsoft i think is somewhat more
prescriptive in that our base class
library the stuff that's included by
default has
everything from regular expressions to
math to
representations of memory all the way up
to putting buttons on the screen
so you don't always have to go out to
the third party
until it's time to get into higher level
abstractions
and that has made net historically
attractive to
enterprises because when you're picking
a framework
and it has a whole ton of ecosystem
things
who do you throttle when it doesn't work
right there's an old joke
that people picked ibm because they got
it gave them one throat to choke
people who are in enterprises typically
will buy
a microsoft thing and then they'll buy a
support license and then they can call
microsoft when it doesn't work
now in the fast forward 20 years
microsoft has a balance between
a strong base class library and a rich
open source environment
so it's a little bit more complicated
but the historical context behind why
microsoft ended up in enterprises is
because of that base class library and
all of those libraries that were
available out of the box
and that's sort of in direct contrast to
something like say javascript where
people are used to
going to the node package manager and
getting a whole bunch of different
dependencies that have been developed by
other people
it sounds like with net the philosophy
is more that
microsoft is going to to give you most
of what you'll need and you can sort of
stay in that
in that environment i would say that
that was the original philosophy i would
say that that was pre-open source
microsoft so maybe 10
10 15 years ago i would think that that
is not a philosophy that is very
conducive to a healthy open source
ecosystem but it was early on when it
was like
here's a thing you kind of buy you
didn't really buy it like it comes with
windows and you buy visual studio
when i joined about 13 14 years ago
myself and others started really pushing
open source because we came from the
open source community
and as we started introducing things
like azure and
services dot net is free has been free
is now open source visual studio code
visual studio community are all free
so the stuff i work on i actually have
nothing to sell
as such it's better to have a healthy
community so we have things like
nuget so nuget and n-u-g-e-t is the same
as npm is the same as maven
it's our package manager environment and
that is
allows you to pull both microsoft
libraries and third-party libraries
and we want to encourage an open source
community that then you know pays open
source framework creators for their work
uses things like github sponsors
people who are working in enterprises
now need to understand that if you pick
just the stuff that microsoft gives you
out of the box you may be limited
in the diversity of cool stuff that's
happening but if you go and start using
open source technology
you might need to go and pay a support
contract for those different tools or
frameworks
depending on whether it's a you know a
reimagination of asp.net or web
framework you say
i don't like the one microsoft has i'm
going to use this one
or an oauth identity server that
microsoft does not ship out of the box
it's a missing piece therefore use this
third-party
identity server what are some things
that
you or microsoft has done to encourage
people
to build open source stuff for net
well early on microsoft was you know
attempted to open source.net
by creating a thing called rotor
r-o-t-o-r
which was a way of saying hey java
everyone in
in academia is using java we have one
too
but it didn't exist the only real open
source licenses at the time were gpl so
microsoft made
a very awkward this is about 20 years
ago very awkward overture where it's
like
here's a zip file with a weird license
that microsoft made called
the mspl the microsoft permissive
license and and here's a kind of a
neutered
version of net that you could
potentially use and
it wasn't source it wasn't open source
it was source opened
it's like here's a zip file like go go
play with this there were no take backs
fundamentally microsoft was not a member
of the open source community
they were just like hey look we have one
too when we started creating asp.net
mvc the model view controller stuff
which is kind of the ruby on
railsfor.net
the decision was made by a bunch of
folks on the team that i worked on and
encouraged by me and others who think
like me just open source the thing and
do take backs it's it's not just
hey there's hey you can watch us write
code and do nothing about it
but the take backs is so important the
rise of github and social coding enabled
that even more
so now actually about 60 of.net comes
from outside microsoft it is truly
collaborative
now microsoft used to patent a bunch of
stuff they'd patent stuff
all over the place and everyone would be
worried i don't want to commit to this
because it might be patented
but then they made the patent promise to
say that any of the patents that
cover.net
won't be things that will be enforced
and then they donated.net
to the.net foundation which is a third
party foundation
much like many other open source
foundations and net
and all of the things within it the
logos and the code the copyrights are
all owned by that
so if microsoft god forbid were to
disappear
or stop caringabout.net it is the
communities that can be built
and deployed and run entirely outside of
dotnet so
it's overtures like that to try to make
sure that people understand that this
isn't going anywhere
it's truly open source and then
takebacks is such a big thing and this
has been going on now for
for many many years most people who
think.net and probably the folks that
are
listening to the show are thinking the
big giant enterprise monolith that only
runs on windows that came out in the
early 2000s
now it is a lightweight cross-platform
open source framework that runs in
containers and a dozen linuxes and
raspberry pi's it's totally open and
it's totally open source all the way
down the compiler's open source
all the libraries everything to your
point of people
picturing net being closed source
running only on windows
i think an important component to that
is the fact that there have been
multiple net run times right there's
been
the framework there's been core there's
been mono
i i wonder if you could elaborate a
little bit on on what each of those are
and what role they they fit in today
that is a very
very astute and important observation so
if i were to take
java byte code i've taken java source
code and i've turned it into java byte
code
there are multiple java runtimes java
vms
that one could call upon there's from
oracle there's
zeus and there's different open source
open jvms and whatnot
there are even interpreters you can run
that through a whole series of them
there's like
you can imagine a pie chart of all the
different java
vms that are available now certainly
there's the 80 case
but there are lots of other ones the
same thing
applied in the net ecosystem there is
the dotnet framework that shipped
and ships continually still with windows
the.net framework and its associated clr
i would say is a and i'm putting my
fingers in quotes here
a dotnet but to your point there are
multiple
dot nets plural mono is a really
interesting one because it is an
open source clean room re-implementation
of the original windowsbased.net
and clean room in that they did not look
at the source code they looked at the
interface
so if i said to you jeremy here's the
interface for system.string
write me an implementation of this
interface
here are the unit tests and you wrote
yourself a jeremy
specific system.string and it worked it
passed all the tests
now you know who knows under load it
might behave differently but for the
most part you made a
a clean room reimplementation of that
mono did that
for all of net proper
but then that became a new.net so for
those that are you know listening they
can't see us or see a screencast but
imagine
that i go out to the command line and
with a microsoft implementation of.net i
make a new console app
it says console.writeline then i compile
it
into an executable i can then run that
with
mono so i created it on one environment
and i ran it with another so i
i did the compilation and the first the
first bit of chewing
and then the finally the jitter would
run through mono because
the il language is itself a standard
that has been submitted to the standards
organizations and it is a thing
so if you and i were you know advanced
computer science students in university
that might be an interesting homework
assignment write
a il interpreter or write an il
jitter and if you can successfully
consume
il that has been created by one of these
many dot nets
you have passed the course then.net core
is a complete reimplementation open
source cross-platform
with no specific ties to windows and
that's the dotnet
that is kind of we're hoping we'll be
rebranded just.net so
five years from now people won't think
about.netcore.net framework they'll just
think about.net
it will run great on windows it'll run
great on linux it'll run great in the
cloud
yada yada yada that is a kind of a
third.net
we're trying to unify all of those with
the releaseof.net 5
which just came out and net five we
picked the number because it's greater
than four
which was the last version of dot net on
windows
but we also skipped a number because net
poor three would have been confusing if
we named it done at core 4 again
microsoft not being good at naming stuff
you imagine two lines heading to the
right.netframework.net core
they then converge into one.net the idea
being to have
one clr one common language runtime one
set of compilers and one base class
library
so that if someone were to learn that if
we hearken back to the
the middle of the beginning of our
conversation when i said that there was
a
theoretical.net developer out there
who's a gamer and there's another one
who's doing back-end work
they should be using the same libraries
they should be using the same languages
they should have a familiarity
with everything up to but not including
the implementation specific details
of their systems so that if a unity
person or a
uh decides to become a back-end
developer or a back-end developer
decides to move over to make iphone
games they're going to say oh
this is all the system.this and that
stuff i'm familiar with that's a
system.string
i appreciate that as opposed to picking
an iphone or an android specific
implementation of a library
if.net core is the open source
re-implementation of the dot-net
framework and you've also got
you were talking about how mono is this
clean room implementation of it
what role does does mono play currently
good question so mono was originally
created by
miguel de acaza and the folks that were
trying to actually make an outlook
competitor on linux
that then turned into the xamarin
company
x-a-r-i-u-m and xamarin then
was a different re-implementation which
allowed them to do
interesting stuff like can we take that
il and send it over to
doing a thing called s-gen and
generating code that would run in an
iphone
or code that would run on an android and
they created a whole mobile ecosystem
and then microsoft bought them
so then because mono and net work on the
same
team we're getting together right now
and we're actively merging those
together now originally mono was really
well known that it was
just nice solid clean c code you could
basically clone the repo
run configure run make and it would
build
while the windows implementation of.net
core and dot-net core in general
wasn't super easy to build it wasn't
just a clone configure and make
a lot of work has been done to make the
best parts of mono
be the best parts of.net core as opposed
to like
disassembling one and you know taking
them apart and making this franken build
we want to make it so net core is is a a
reimagining of both
the original dotted framework on windows
and the best of across platform one
so that is currently in the process in
that.net5.net six waves so this year
in november we will release dotnet six
and that will also be an lts or a long
term support
release so those of you who are familiar
with ubuntu's
concept of lts those long long term
support versions will have
you know many years three years plus of
of support
and by then the mono dot net merge will
kind of be complete
and then you'll find that.netcore will
basically run everywhere that mono would
that doesn't mean mono as an ecosystem
goes away it just becomes
another not the supported version of
net at a runtime level when we look at
the java virtual machine and we look at
that ecosystem
there are languages like scala and
closure
things that were not made by the creator
of the jvm
but are new languages that target that
runtime and
i i wonder from your perspective why
there was never that sort of
community with the common language
runtime
i would think that because the interest
from academia
early on 20 years ago was primarily
around java
and microsoft was slow on the uptake
from an open source perspective
that slowed down possible
implementations of other languages
and then net got so popular and c sharp
evolved because c sharp is now on
version nine the c sharp that you wrote
the idiomatic c
sharp of 2001 is not the idiomatic c
sharp
which includes you know records and
async and await and
and interesting things that have shown
up on c-sharp and then been borrowed
by other languages async and await being
a great example link
language integrated query being another
things that didn't exist that language
has evolved
fast enough that people didn't feel that
it was worth the effort
and it was really f sharp that picked an
entirely different philosophy in the in
the functional way by
doing kind of an o camel style thing and
because c-sharp and f-sharp are so
different from each other
they really fit nicely they're as
different as
english and another language that isn't
latin based you know and
meaning that they add flavor to the
environment that doesn't mean that there
aren't going to continue to be
niche languages but there was also
things like iron ruby and iron python
but they weren't really needed because
the python and ruby runtimes already
worked quite well
we've been talking about net and sort of
the parts that
makeup.net but i was wondering other
languages
have niches right you have go maybe
for more systems type programming or
python for machine learning like are
there niches for
net oh yeah i mean so one i
would i would i would generally push
back on the idea of niche though because
i don't want to use niche as a
diminutive
right i kind of like the term domain
specific just in the sense of
you know you know when in finland speak
finnish
that doesn't mean that we would say hey
you know finnish didn't win
like we're not all speaking it's not the
it's not the language that won
but we don't want to think about things
like that there are great languages
that exist for a reason because people
want to do different stuff with them
so for example a really well thought of
language in the dot net space is f sharp
and f sharp is a functional language so
for people who are familiar with
oh camel and haskell and things like
that people who want to go and create
a language that is you know very correct
very maintainable very clear that has
a real focus on you managing the problem
domain
as opposed to the details of imperative
programming
it has immutable data structures by
default there's a lot more type
inference than there is in c-sharp a lot
of people use f-sharp in the financial
services
industry and it also has some
interesting language features like
records and discriminated unions
that c-sharp people are just now kind of
getting hip to
what i typically see or what i think
people
sort of believe when they they think
of.net as they think of enterprise
applications
and i'm wondering if you have some
examples of things that are sort of
beyond that space
sure so when i think of.net like in the
past i would think of like
big windows apps with giant rows of tabs
and text boxes over data you know if i
go to my eye doctor and i see the giant
weird application that he's running
that's multiple colors and a lot of
grids and
stuff and i think oh that must be
written in.net those are the
applications of 20 years ago
the other thing that i think people
think about when they think about.net is
it's a thing that is tied to windows and
built on windows and probably takes
about
gigabytes of space dotnet core is meant
to be
more like node and more like go than it
is to be like
net framework so for example if i were
to create a microservice
using.net core i go out to the command
line and i type
dotnet new web or dot net new empty or
dot net new console
and then i can say dot net publish and i
can bring in a run time now we talked it
before about how
you could keep things very non-specific
until the last minute and let the run
time on the deployed machine decide
or you could say you know this is going
to a raspberry pi it's going to be a
micro service on a raspberry pi i want
it to be as small as possible
so there's multiple steps we've gone and
we made this little micro service and we
published it
then we publish all of the support dlls
the dynamic link libraries the shared
objects if it's going to linux
all of the native bindings that
that provide that binding between the
runtime and the native processor
and the native operating system all the
system calls
then that is right now about 150 180
megs on.net
but then we look at the tree of
function calls and we say you know this
is a micro service it only does like six
things
looks at the weather it calls like six
native functions
then we do what's called tree trimming
or tree shaking and we shake we give it
a good shake
and then we basically delete all of the
functions that are never
called and we know those things right we
can we can introspect
the code and we can shake this thing and
we can get
microservices down to 30 40 megs
now again you might say well compared to
go or compared to writing that in c
sure but you're talking about still
maintaining
the jitter the garbage collector the
strongly typed
abilities of net all of the great
features of this cool environment
shaken down to you know 30 40 megs and
then you can pack that tightly into a
container
even better if the container layer above
it and if you imagine a multi-stage
docker container
doesn't include the compiler doesn't
include the sdk and the container above
it includes the runtime itself
you might only deploy 1015 megs you can
really pack nicely together a.net
microservice and then a whole series of
them thousands of them potentially into
something like kubernetes
that's a very fundamentally different
thing than the giant.net application
that took two gigs on your
on your hard drive this is the cool part
though
that giant we call it windows forms or
that wpf that windows presentation
application
that um often we find in large
enterprises
moves slowly because the
and not run slowly but move slowly from
an um from a devops perspective
because the enterprise is afraid to
update it or they need to wait for
windows to get the version of.net that
they want
because.net has historically been tied
to windows
which sucks then that application and
the whole team behind it
gets depressed what if we could take the
cool benefits that i just described
around containers
back port it so that that giant
application in my doctor's office
ships its own local copy of net
which it can then maintain manage and
deal with its it's on its own
all in a local folder doesn't need to
wait for windows
that's really cool then they could do
that pre-jitting basically do a native
image generation
and even create a single executable
where inside is.net so that i give you
my doctor's office.exe you double-click
on it you install nothing
it simply unfolds like a flower into
memory
including all of the benefits now it's
not generated native code at this point
right it's dot net
in an envelope that then blooms and then
runs
with all native dependencies that it
needs that is pretty cool and that
actually regenerates
excitement in the enterprises so that
they can bring those older applications
to modern techniques like devops and as
well as a huge
huge perf speed up like 2x 3x per speed
up
when you talk about a perf speed of why
would
including the net runtime with the
application result in a perf speed up
it's not that we're including the dotnet
runtime that caused the perf speed up
it's that 20 years of improvement in
jitter
20 years of understanding the garbage
collector rather than using the dotnet
that shipped with windows
they can use the one that understands
again a callback to the beginning
instruction sets that are newer and
modern simd
sse2 all the different things that one
could potentially
exploit when on a newer system those
things
are we get huge numbers and actually.net
itself.net five is like two or three x
over.net core three
which is two or three x over so a huge
push has been happening
and actually all the benchmarks are
public so if you go to
tech m power the tech em power
benchmarks
you can see that we're having a
wonderfully fun kind of competition a
bit of a thumb war
with you know the goes and the javas and
the you know groovion
rails of the world to the point where
we're actually bumping up against the
laws of physics
we can put out you know seven or eight
million requests a second
and then you notice that we all bundle
at the top and net kind of moves within
a couple of percentage of another one
and the reason is is that we've
saturated the network so without a 10
gigabit network there's literally
nothing no more bytes can be pushed
so net is no longer in the middle or to
the far
right of the of the long tail of the
curve we're right up against
anything else and sometimes as fast as
10x
faster than things like node so it
sounds like
going from the.net framework to net core
and
rebuilding that you've been able to get
these giant speed improvements
you were giving the example of a windows
desktop application and saying
that you could take this that was built
for the dot-net framework
and run it on.net core i'm wondering is
that
a case where somebody can just take
their existing project take their
existing code and just choose to run it
or
is does there have to be some kind of
conversion process
so that's a great question so it depends
on if you're doing anything that is like
super specific or weird like if you were
a weird application then then you might
bump up against an edge case
the same thing the same thinking applies
if you were trying to take an
application cross-platform
for example i did a tiny mini virtual
machine and an operating system for a
an advanced class in computer science 15
20 years ago
i was able to take that application
which was written and compiled on.net
1.1
and move it to.net core and run in a
container and then run on a raspberry pi
because it was completely abstract it
was using
byte arrays and list of t and kind of
pretty straightforward base class
library stuff it didn't call the
registry
it didn't call any windows apis so i was
able to take a 15 year old app
and move it in about a day another
example my blog
which used to run on.net 2 my blog is
over 19 years old now
has recently been ordered from.net 2
to 4 then.net core and now.net 5
runs in the cloud in linux in a
container
with 80 of the code the same the stuff
that isn't the same that i had to
actually
consciously work around with the help of
my friend mark downey
was well we called the registry the
registry is a windows thing it doesn't
exist
so what's the you know what's the
implementation is it a json file now is
it an xml file
when it runs in a container it needs to
talk to certain mapped file system
things while before it was assuming
backslashes or a c colon so
implementation details
need to to move over another thing that
is interesting to point out though is
that there are
primitives there are language and
runtime primitives
that didn't exist before that exist now
and one of the most important one
is a thing that's called span of t
span less than uppercase t greater than
and this is the idea of a completely new
way of thinking about
arbitrary continuous bits of memory do
you want to be at a high level language
and then messing around in byte arrays
or do you want to think about things
at that higher level but then also avoid
reallocation and copying of memory
around so something very simple like
some http headers come in if you're
doing seven million of these a second
this can add up right
and it's like well usually we take a
look at that
chunk of memory and we copy it into an
array and then we start using higher
level
constructs to deal with that now i have
a list of char and then we for loop
around the list of char
that's kind of gross and then you find
out that you're
hitting the garbage collector a lot
because you're allocating memory and
you're copying stuff around
you could take that older code update it
to use
span of t and represent that contiguous
region of arbitrary memory differently
rather than an array a span can point to
native memory or even memory managed on
a stack
and then deal with stuff for example
parsing or
maneuvering within http headers with no
allocations
so a really great example you'd ask for
an example of an application that you
couldn't believe
vr desktop are you familiar with vr
desktop as it relates to the oculus
quest
no so the oculus quest is the facebook
vr thing right
and it's an android phone on your face
and it's you can use it unplugged
and then people say well i've got this
android phone on my face i'd really like
to plug it in with a usb
cable and use the power of my desktop
but then i got to ship those bits across
the usb
and then have a client application that
allows me to use it as a dumb client
you would expect an application that
someone would write to do that would be
written in
c or c plus or something really low
level
vr desktop allows you to actually see
your windows desktop
and ship those bits across the wire
across the literal wire the usb
3 or wirelessly is written entirely in c
sharp
and you can use really smart memory
allocation techniques and the trick is
don't allocate any memory and c-sharp is
more than fast enough to have
less than 20 millisecond jitter on
frames
so that it is buttery smooth even over
wireless and i did a whole podcast
on that with the ghee gouda the canadian
gentleman who wrote vr desktop that's
really
interesting because you're talking about
areas where
typically when you think of a managed
language
like c sharp you're able to use it in
more environments than you
you might normally think of and i also
kind of wonder
you have the new
apple machines coming out they have
their arm processors instead of the
x86 processors what is the the state of
net when targeting an arm environment
can somebody
simply take that il that's on one
machine bring it on to the arm machine
and it just works
yep so if you are putting if you're
taking over the
the il and i'm on a windows machine
right now i'm on an x64 machine and i
go.net new
console and i go.net run and it works on
my x64 machine
and i say net publish i can then
take that that library over to the
raspberry pi or an arm machine
say dot net run and because i'm saying
it run with the local
dot net runtime it will pick up that il
and it will just run
so i have run using my now 19 20 year
old blog as an example
i have run that entire blog on a
raspberry pi
unchanged once i had worked out the
portability issues like backslashes
versus forward slashes and assumptions
like that
so once the underlying syscalls line up
absolutely
and we actually announced in july of
2020 that we will support dot net core
on the new mac hardware there are
requirements for dot net and dot net
core
on you know apple like arm 64 and big
sur that would be required
to get that runtime working but yes the
goal would be to have native processes
versus rosetta two processes working and
that work is happening
we were talking about like the typical
enterprise application
you've got a windows forms application
is it possible for somebody with an
application like that to
to target arm so right now
there's there's multiple layers so the
compiler yes
the runtime yes the application yes at
the point where if i were going to run
on windows arm like a surface pro x or
something like that
we would need support for i believe
windows forms winforms and wpf
i don't know that those are working
right now but those apps still run
because just like we have the rosetta
emulator
i can emulate x6 x86 stuff so for
example paint.net is a great
net application that is basically
photoshop but it's four bucks
that it runs entirely on.net core and it
runs just fine on a surface pro x in an
emulated state
and i believe that the intent of course
is to get everything running everywhere
so yeah i would
be sad if it didn't that's a little
outside my group
but the people that are working on that
stuff and by the way the great thing
about this
go and look at the github issues right
so you know if you look on i'm looking
right now on a.net issue
4879 where they're talking about the
plan is supporting.net core
3 and 5 on rosetta 2 via emulation and
net 6 supported in both native m1
architecture
and rosetta 2 and there's in fact a.net
runtime
tracking issue that's called support
apple silicon
and they walk through where they're at
current status on both mono and
net six it's cool because you get to
like actually see what we're doing right
like before you had to know somebody
at microsoft and then call your friend
and be like hey what's going on we are
literally doing the work
in open on github so if the if the tech
journalist would pay more attention to
the actual
commits they would get like scoops weeks
before on a blog post came out because
they're like i just saw the
you know the check-in for you know the
apple silicon show up in the dot-net but
uh might get a little bit technical for
the average journalist though
one of the things that you've been
talking about is how with dot net core
you have a lot of cross
platform capabilities i wonder from
an adoption standpoint what you've seen
like are there people
actually running their services and
linux and docker
kubernetes that sort of thing yeah
dot-net one of the things that we try to
make sure that it works everywhere so
we've seen huge numbers not only on
azure but aws
has a very burgeoning.net community as
well as their sdks all work on.net same
with google cloud
we're trying to be really friendly and
supportive of anyone
because i want it to run everywhere so
for example at our recent.net conf which
is our little virtual conference that we
make
we had kelsey hightower from google
cloud like their main google cloud
kubernetes person
learn.net in a weekend and then deploy
to kubernetes on google cloud
we're seeing a huge uptick on net five
so that
unified version where we took dot net
core and the dotted framework and
unified them
it's the most quickly adopted.net ever
i mentioned before that like 60 of the
commits are coming from outside the
community we're seeing
big numbers you know stack overflow is
moving to dot has moved to.net core
they're actually showing their perf most
of the games that you run are already
running on.net you know if you see a
unity game there's dot-net
and c-sharp running in that a lot of the
mobile games that you're seeing
one of the other things that we're
noticing is that more more and more
students and
young people are getting involved so
we're really trying to put a lot of work
into that one of the other things that's
kind of cool that we should talk about
before the end
is a thing called blazer have you heard
about that yeah maybe you could explain
it to our audience
so just like um if we use ruby on rails
as an example i like to use other
frameworks as an example like builds
cool stuff on top of it so it's like you
pick your ruby
whether it be jruby or mrb or whatever
and then you've got your
framework on top of that and then other
frameworks and you layer in your layer
in your layer
dot net has this thing called asp.net
activeserverpages.net it's a stupid old
name
you can make web apis that are json and
xml based apis
you can make standard model view
controller type of environments
you can do a thing called razer pages
where you can basically mix and match
c-sharp and html but if you want to do
those higher level
enterprise applications where you just
don't want to learn javascript
we've actually taken the clr
and compiled it to wasm web assembly
and we can run the clr inside v8
then if you actually hit f12 tools on a
blazer page
laser is b l a z o r you hit f12
you go and you hit a blazer page you can
see the dlls the actual dynamic link
libraries coming over the wire
and then the intermediate language that
we've been talking about so much on this
podcast
gets interpreted on the client side
which allows a whole new family of
people
that already know c sharp like those
individuals that we spoke to
spoke about at the beginning you've got
someone with 10 years experience in
unity and
everyone else got 10 years experience on
the back end they never got around to
learning javascript
they can write c sharp they can target
the browser
and then the browser itself runs net and
then blazer
allows them to create spa applications
single page applications
much like gmail and twitter and pwas
progressive web apps so one could go and
create
an app and rather than an electron kind
of an app which is using javascript and
a whole host of tools
they can make a blazer app have it run
natively anywhere
they can then pin it to their mobile
phone or their
taskbar on windows and they're they're
suddenly a web developer and it's a
really great environment for those big
enterprise applications
or those more line of business type apps
because the data binding is just so
clean
and then that back end can be anything
so blazer is a really great environment
and a pretty interesting technical
achievement to get net itself
running within the context of the
browser does that mean that
somehow you've been able to fit the
net core runtime in webassembly i'm
trying to understand how that works yeah
yep that's exactly that's exactly right
so remember how we mentioned before that
this isn't the multi-gigabyte thing that
everyone is so afraid of
you basically bring down i think it's
like 15 or 20 megs which is
you know a little bit big but if you
think about the home page of the verge
it's not that big right i've seen pngs
bigger than the.net runtime
once you bring that down of course if
you put that on on a cdn
that's handled i think it's actually
even smaller than that it's not that big
of a deal because once it's down it's
cached
and that is really the net core
you know mono runtime running within the
context of
webassembly and then you're just calling
local browser things but here's the cool
part
let's say you don't like any of that
let's say i've described this whole
thing
you like the application model i want to
write c sharp
but you don't want to download and like
put a lot of work into
getting the local cpu and the local v8
implementation to do that
you can actually not run the dotnet
framework in the dot net core rather
pardon me
on the client side but you can have it
run on the
server side and then you open a
socket between the front end and the
back end
but then the events that occur on the
client side gets shuttled over web
sockets to a
stateful server so there's blazer
which is client side and then there's
blazer server
which means it can run anywhere on any
device so then it's more of a
programming model thing
you still don't have to write any
javascript because you'll be addressing
the dom the document object model within
the browser
from the server side the messaging then
goes magically
over the websockets you basically you
have a persistent
channel bus running between the front
and the back end
so you get to choose yeah we did a show
on phoenix live view and it sounds like
this is a very
similar concept except that you get the
choice of
having that run in the server or run
locally in the client
yeah and i think the folks on ruby on
rails are doing similar kinds of things
it's this idea of
you know bringing html back maybe
getting a little less javascript heavy
and really thinking about
shoving around islands of marked markup
right
if i have a pretty basic you know master
detail page and i click on something and
i just want to send back a card
does that really need to be a full-blown
react view angular application
the idea is you you make a call to get
some data you
ship the html back and you swap out a
div so it's trying to find a balance
between
too much javascript and too many post
backs
and i think it hits a nice balance
blazer is seeing huge pickup
particularly in people who have found
javascript to be somewhat daunting
i think we've been talking about things
that are a little more
cutting edge in terms of what's
happening in the dotnet
ecosystem things like web assembly
what else are microsoft's priorities for
the future of
net are you hoping to move into some
more ahead of time
compilation environments for example
where you need something really small
that can run on iot type devices
what's the the future of net
from your perspective all of the above
if you take a look at the microsoft.net
iot
repository in github we've got bindings
for dozens and dozens and dozens of
sensors and screens and things like that
we have partnerships with folks like pi
top so if you're teaching.net
you can go in inside of your browser in
a jupiter
kind of an environment go and
communicate with actual physical
hardware and call
gpio general purpose io directly we're
also partnering with folks like
wilderness
labs which has a wonderful
implementation of.net
based on mono that allows you to write
straight c sharp
on a tiny microprocessor not a
micro controller pardon me rather than a
microprocessor and create
you know commercial grade applications
like
a you know a thermostat running in.net
which again
takes those different people that i've
mentioned before who have familiarity
with the ecosystem
but maybe not familiarity with the
deployment and turns them into
iot developers so there's a huge group
of people that are thinking about stuff
like that
we've also seen 60 frame a second games
being written in the browser
using blazer so we are finding that it
is performant enough to go and do
you know we've seen gradius and
different games like that being
implemented using the canvas
with laser server running at its uh at
its heart
the intent is for it to be kind of a
great environment for everyone anywhere
and then if you go to the.net website
which is at d dot.net.net
we can actually run it in the browser
and write the code and hit run so you
can learn.net without downloading
anything
and then there's also some excitement
around.net interactive notebooks
which allows you to use f-sharp and
c-sharp in
jupyter notebooks and mix and match it
with different languages
you could have javascript d3js
some svg visualizations using c-sharp
all in the browser entirely in the in
the jupyter notebooks
ipymb ecosystem so when you talk about
net everywhere it's really increasing
the number
of domains that you can use dot net in
like
be the person who maybe you built
enterprise windows applications before
but now you're able to take those same
skills and like you said make a game or
something like that
bingo exactly that doesn't mean that you
can't or shouldn't be a polyglot but the
idea is that there's this really great
ecosystem that already exists
why shouldn't those people be enabled to
have fun anywhere
i think that's a great note to end on so
for people who want to check out what
you're up to
or learn more about.net where should
they head
well they can find me just by googling
for hanselman
google with bing if it makes you happy
everything i've got is linked off of
hanselman.com
and then if they're interested in
learning more about.net they can go to
you know just googleford.net and you'll
find.net.microsoft.com
within the download page you'll see that
we work on mac
linux docker windows if you already have
visual studio code
just download the.net sdk go to the
command line type.net new console and
open it up in visual studio code
vs code will automatically get the
extensions that you need and you can
start playing around
feel free to ask me any questions we've
got a whole community section of our
website
whether it be stack overflow or reddit
or discord or code newbies or tick tock
we are there and we want to make you
successful very cool well
scott thank you so much for chatting
with me today thank you i appreciate
your very deep questions and you clearly
did your research and i appreciate that
this has been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio
thanks for listening thanks for
listening to sc radio an educational
program brought to you by ieee software
magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
sc radio dots
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening